<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<justice xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" creator="http://courtlabs.org" created="2012-04-16T11:08:36" modified="2013-07-12T19:14:31" license="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/">
  <justiceName id="henry_b_brown">Henry B. Brown</justiceName>
  <justiceBirthDate formatted="Wednesday, March 2, 1836">1836-03-02</justiceBirthDate>
  <justiceDeathDate formatted="Thursday, September 4, 1913">1913-09-04</justiceDeathDate>
  <justiceAppointment>
    <justicePosition>Associate Justice</justicePosition>
    <justiceSeat>6</justiceSeat>
    <justiceNominatedBy>Harrison</justiceNominatedBy>
    <justiceCommissionedDate formatted="Sunday, December 28, 1890">1890-12-28</justiceCommissionedDate>
    <justiceSwornDate formatted="Sunday, January 4, 1891">1891-01-04</justiceSwornDate>
    <justiceEndDate formatted="Sunday, May 27, 1906">1906-05-27</justiceEndDate>
    <justiceReasonForLeaving>Retired</justiceReasonForLeaving>
    <justiceLengthofService>15 years, 4 months, 23 days</justiceLengthofService>
    <justiceHome>Michigan</justiceHome>
  </justiceAppointment>
  <justiceBiography>
    <p>
      <span>Henry Billings Brown was born and raised in a small Massachusetts town. He led a privileged life, and was a good though undistinguished student. He avoided service in the Civil War by hiring a substitute, an accepted practice in his day.</span>
    </p>
    <p>
      <span>Brown held several government positions at the federal and state levels. He was a well-regarded federal judge in Michigan when Howell Edmonds Jackson, a former senator and friend of President Harrison, urged Brown's move to the Supreme Court. Brown returned Jackson's favor by urging Harrison to "bring up" Jackson three years later.</span>
    </p>
    <p>
      <span>Brown authored in excess of 450 majority opinions during his years on the Court. He gave preference to private property claims and he defended free competition. But Brown also took a broad view of the state's police powers including governmental restrictions on laissez faire.</span>
    </p>
    <p>
      <span>Brown will probably be forever marked by a single opinion he authored for a majority: Plessy v. Ferguson. Brown no doubt reflected the view of his day that whites were biologically separate from blacks and that whites were superior to blacks as a group.</span>
    </p>
  </justiceBiography>
  <justiceImageLarge>/justices/henry_b_brown/image-large.jpg</justiceImageLarge>
  <justiceImageSmall>/justices/henry_b_brown/image-small.jpg</justiceImageSmall>
  <justiceImageAttribution>The Collection of the Supreme Court of the United States (Artist: Lewis Thomas Ives)</justiceImageAttribution>
</justice>
